<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The church's security in the midst of all difficulties and dangers explain'd and asserted in a sermon preacht upon the 5th of November last, upon those words of Numb. 23, 23 / by R.W., B.D., and minister of Kedarminster in the county of Worcester.</title>
            <author>White, Richard, b. 1636.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65766</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1802</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9789</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12643326</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12643326</idno>
            <idno type="VID">65060</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65766)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 65060)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 338:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The church's security in the midst of all difficulties and dangers explain'd and asserted in a sermon preacht upon the 5th of November last, upon those words of Numb. 23, 23 / by R.W., B.D., and minister of Kedarminster in the county of Worcester.</title>
                  <author>White, Richard, b. 1636.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Parkhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Richard White. Cf. Halkett &amp; Laing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Numbers XXIII, 23 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:65060:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Church's Security In the midſt of All Difficulties and Dangers, Explain'd, and aſſerted, in a SERMON Preacht upon the 5th of <hi>November</hi> laſt, Upon thoſe words of <hi>Numb.</hi> 23.23.</p>
            <p>By <hi>R. W.</hi> B. D. And Miniſter of <hi>Kedarminſter,</hi> in the County of <hi>Worceſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt,</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns,</hi> the lower End of <hi>Cheapſide.</hi> 1694.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:65060:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:65060:2"/>
            <head>To the Worſhipful, The
<list>
                  <item>High-Bayliff,</item>
                  <item>Juſtice,</item>
                  <item>Aldermen;</item>
               </list> And the reſt of the Corporation of <hi>Kedarminſter.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen!</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOU being generally my Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors, at the Time of my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livering this Enſuing Diſcourſe, were quicken'd from what you have heard, to make it your general deſire, by the Mediation of ſeveral of the Chief amongſt you, that I would make my late Diſcourſe more Publick, by the Printing of it: This being the firſt Requeſt in this kind, which you ever made unto me; I am therefore
<pb facs="tcp:65060:3"/>the more willing to comply with it, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially conſidering, that I know not how much of a Call from Providence, there may be in your ſo general Concurrence, in this matter: I commit the Enſuing Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to the Divine Bleſſing, and you all to the Divine Protection, ſubſcribing my ſelf,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Affectionate Miniſter, R. W.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Nov. <hi>13. 1693.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:65060:3"/>
            <head>The Church's Security, &amp;c.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Numbers 23.23.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Surely there is no Inchantment againſt <hi>Jacob,</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is there any Divination againſt <hi>Iſrael;</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this time it ſhall be ſaid of <hi>Jacob</hi> and of <hi>Iſrael, What hath God wrought?</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THESE words were uttered by <hi>Balaam,</hi> when he endeavoured to curſe <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the People of God, that ſo he might obtain a reward from <hi>Balak;</hi> he was in himſelf no better than a Witch or Conjurer; but when he ſought to do miſchief to God's People by the aſſiſtance of evil, and wicked Spirits with whom he was confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, the holy Spirit of God did ſtrangely inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and made uſe of this Conjurer to be his Inſtrument for Prophecy as to ſeveral particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars that relate to the Church of God in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, and for the declaring of a Bleſſing to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which was God's Peculiar and Choſen People, his Church at that preſent time; and ſo God by the over-ruling power of his Spirit, did turn the Curſe, that was intended by this wicked In chanter, into a Bleſſing.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:65060:4"/>
            <p>More eſpecially, in the words of my Text, there is a diſcovery made, by the plain confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of this Wizzard, of the vanity of his own attempts, againſt the Church and People of God; <hi>Surely,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>there is no Inchantment againſt</hi> Jacob, <hi>neither is there any Divination againſt</hi> Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſrael, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as before.</p>
            <p>In which words we have contain'd two ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral parts.</p>
            <p n="1">1. An Aſſertion firmly laid down, with rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Iſrael; Surely,</hi> or aſſuredly, as if he had ſaid, you may take this for an aſſured thing, for a certain truth, that <hi>there is no Inchant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt</hi> Jacob, <hi>neither is there any Divination againſt</hi> Iſrael. We know that the names <hi>Jacob,</hi> and <hi>Iſrael,</hi> were both of them firſt given to him, who was the Father of thoſe twelve Patriarchs, from whom were derived thoſe twelve Tribes, of which the Jewiſh Nation was conſtituted. The name <hi>Jacob</hi> ſignifies a Wreſtler, or a Supplanter, and was given to him at firſt, upon occaſion of his laying hold, of his Brother <hi>Eſau</hi>'s heel, at his Birth, and was further confirm'd to him after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, in the fitneſs of its ſignification, by his ſupplanting his Brother <hi>Eſau,</hi> and depriving him, both of the Birth right, and of the Bleſſing; and alſo again in his famous wreſtling with God by Faith, and Prayer, as well as with the Angel of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:65060:4"/>God by bodily exerciſe; from the ſucceſs of which wreſtling, it alſo came to paſs, that the other name here mention'd, the name of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> was given un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, that is, a Prince with God, according to the words of the Angel, <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.28. <hi>And he ſaid, thy name ſhall be called no more</hi> Jacob, <hi>but</hi> Iſrael, <hi>for as a Prince, haſt thou power with God, and with Men, and haſt prevailed.</hi> Theſe names <hi>Jacob,</hi> and <hi>Iſrael,</hi> are here, as in many other places, uſed to denote the whole Nation, which derived from this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, there being nothing more common, both in Scripture, and likewiſe in other Authors, than to call a Nation by the name of the Perſon, or Perſons, from whom it proceeded.</p>
            <p>Now foraſmuch as this Nation was the Church and peculiar People of God, above all the Nations of the World, according to that of the Pſalmiſt, <hi>In</hi> Judah <hi>is God known, his name is great in</hi> Iſrael, <hi>at</hi> Salem <hi>alſo is his Tabernacle, and his dwelling-place in</hi> Sion; <hi>he hath not dealt ſo with any Nation,</hi> that is, <hi>with any other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, neither have the Heathen the knowledge of his Law:</hi> For this reaſon it is, that by the names <hi>Jacob,</hi> and <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the Church of God in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, eſpecially that, which we call the Inviſible Church, the Church of the Faithful, of ſuch as are what they profeſs themſelves to be, even real Believers, is to be underſtood, and even in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:65060:5"/>this large ſenſe, are theſe words, <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> to be underſtood here in my Text, even to denote all true Believers the Church of the Faithful throughout all Ages: Theſe are all, (1.) <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Wreſtlers, and that both with rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God and alſo with relation to Men.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They are wont to be Wreſtlers with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to God, by Faith and Prayer; they are not willing to give the Almighty any reſt, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til he eſtabliſh <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> his Church in general, a praiſe in the Earth.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They are Wreſtlers with relation to Men, thoſe that are the Enemies of God, and Chriſt, and true Goodneſs; as in Baptiſm they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roll'd in the number of Chriſt's Souldiers, ſo they make it their buſineſs, to fight under his Banner, againſt the Devil, the World, and the Fleſh, which are his Enemies, and to acquit themſelves well, in their ſpiritual Combate and Warfare; for as the Seed of the Serpent, is an Enemy to the Seed of the Woman; ſo is the Seed of the Woman an Enemy to the Seed of the Serpent; and they do in the iſſue get the Bleſſing from, and prevail againſt thoſe car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>Eſau</hi>'s, who tho' they're Brethren it may be, according to the Fleſh, yet bear an Enmity to them; yea they become at length more than Conquerors over all their ſpiritual Enemies,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:65060:5"/>through Chriſt ſtrengthening of them; which makes it evident,</p>
            <p n="2">2. That all the true Members of the Church of Chriſt, are alſo <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s, ſuch as have power with God, and with Men, and do prevail; as they wreſtle with God by Faith and Prayer, ſo through the Divine Grace and Condeſcention, they are wont to prevail with God by Faith and Prayer: And as they wreſtle and contend in the Cauſe of God againſt Sin, and ſinful Men; ſo they are wont to prevail, and to be Crowned as Conquerors at laſt, tho' it may be even by ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering; ſo that there is enough ſaid for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of theſe two names here mentioned, <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Concerning theſe 'tis here ſaid, that <hi>there is no Inchantment againſt</hi> Jacob, <hi>neither is there any Divination againſt</hi> Iſrael: Some read it, there is no Inchantment in <hi>Jacob,</hi> no Divination in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to denote that God's People do abhor ſuch wicked practices; as in their Baptiſm they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced the Devil, and all his Works; ſo they abhor the thoughts of entring into League with Hell, and of being at an agreement with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction; they abhor ſuch practices, wherein the Devil's aſſiſtance is required and expected. But the plain and moſt obvious ſenſe of the words ſeems to be this, That tho' the Devil and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:65060:6"/>his Inſtruments may deſign the ruine and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Church of God, yet all the Contrivan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Machinations of wicked Men, yea tho' they take in the aſſiſtance of the Devil himſelf, for their help, ſhall not prevail againſt the Church, ſo as to bring ruine and deſtruction upon it; in this ſenſe, to be ſure, <hi>There is no In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chantment againſt</hi> Jacob, <hi>there is no Divination againſt</hi> Iſrael. 'Tis added in my Text. (2.) Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this time, it ſhall be ſaid of <hi>Jacob</hi> and of <hi>Iſrael, What hath God wrought?</hi> The propereſt ſenſe and meaning of which words ſeems to be this; That according to this inſtance here before us, wherein God did fruſtrate all the deſigns of <hi>Balak</hi> and <hi>Balaam,</hi> for the curſing of God's People in that Age, and bringing miſchief upon them; ſo he will deal with his Church and People throughout all Ages; God will repeat the ſame deliverance to his Church and People in all ſucceeding Ages, which he afforded in the inſtance before us; ſo that God's People ſhall have reaſon to ſay, not only in that preſent Age, but alſo in all Ages following, that God is one &amp; the ſame to them, the ſame in Power, and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and Faithfulneſs; according as 'twas ſaid at this time, ſo it ſhall be ſaid in all times following, by <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Iſrael, What hath God wrought?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that the words thus explained, do afford
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:65060:6"/>unto us theſe three Notes, as a ground of fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſcourſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That it is, and hath been all along, and will be more or leſs to the end of the World, the wont and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom of the Devil, and his Inſtruments, to contrive, and deſign the ruine and miſery of the Church and People of God, tho' by the wickedeſt means that can be thought of, or invented.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That the Church and People of God are from time to time, and ſhall be to the end of the World de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered from, and ſhall even prevail againſt the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivances, and machinations of the Devil, and his Inſtruments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>That the whole honour of this is to be aſcribed to God, and muſt be acknowledged to be the effect of his power and operation.</hi> I ſhall reſume theſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, and a little conſider them more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly, in the ſame order in which I have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded them.</p>
            <p>I begin with the firſt; <hi>That it is, and hath been all along, and will be to the end of the World, the wont and cuſtom of the Devil, and his Inſtruments to contrive and deſign the ruine and miſery of the Church and People of God, tho' it be by the wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt means, that can be thought of or invented.</hi> The Hiſtory of all Times, and the many Books of Martyrology, which are extant, will confirm us in this. We have an Inſtance of this, in the moſt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:65060:7"/>early Times of the World, in the caſe of <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel; Cain was of that wicked one, and ſlew his Brother; and wherefore ſlew he him? 'twas becauſe his own works were wicked, and his Brothers were righteous;</hi> as the Apoſtle gives account of this matter, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.12. This was the main ground of the quarrel between them, that one was a true Believer, the Seed of the Woman, a true Member of the Church, and the other was of the Seed of the Serpent, and nothing ſuitably could ſatisfie the Rancour, which <hi>Cain</hi> had conceived within himſelf, but to perſecute his Brother to the Death. Thus <hi>Pharaoh</hi> ſet himſelf againſt the People of God, and was not ſatisfi'd with op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing them by hard bondage and ſervice, but at length took a courſe, which if it had prevail'd, would have deſtroy'd the whole Nation in one Age, and ſo the Church of God contain'd there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; he bethought himſelf of that wicked courſe, of killing all the Male-Infants of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> as ſoon as they were born. Thus it was likewiſe in the Inſtance here before us, to which my Text refers. <hi>Balak</hi> would hire <hi>Balaam,</hi> to make uſe of the power of Witchery, and Divination, that is, to preſs and engage Hell it ſelf, and the powers of Darkneſs, to this work, of curſing the People of God and all to this purpoſe, that he might the more eaſily conſume and deſtroy them. Thus
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:65060:7"/>
               <hi>Haman</hi> laid a Plot not only againſt <hi>Mordecai,</hi> but alſo in order to the ruine of the whole Jewiſh Nation, that were then diſperſed throughout the Perſian-Monarchy, and this to be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſht by no leſs than an Univerſal Maſſacre. Thus the Primitive Chriſtians did wade thro' a Sea of Blood to Heaven; being perſecuted with infinite varieties of Torments in ten ſeveral Bloody Perſecutions from the Heathens, beſides what they endured from the unbelieving Jews, who were alſo their implacable Enemies. And the Blood of Proteſtants, that hath been ſhed by the Papiſts, hath by the account of ſome fallen nothing ſhort of that Chriſtian Blood, that was ſhed by Heathen <hi>Rome,</hi> in the firſt 300 Years of Chriſtianity; and we may find reaſon to believe it to be true, if we conſider thoſe many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands that have been deſtroy'd by Burning, and Maſſacres, almoſt in all Nations of <hi>Europe,</hi> parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly, 60000 Proteſtants maſſacred in <hi>Paris,</hi> and other parts of <hi>France,</hi> in the laſt Age; and 20000 barbarouſly murdered by the Papiſts in <hi>Ireland,</hi> in the memory of ſome here preſent. Add to this the Deſign of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Invaſion in Eighty eight, which tended to the ruining and enſlaving of the whole Engliſh Nation, and the barbarous Slaughter or all, that would not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently have bow'd down to the Idols of <hi>Rome</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:65060:8"/>and <hi>Spain.</hi> Add alſo the Deſign of this Day, which was, with one Blow, to deſtroy the King, and Royal Family, and all the Eſtates of our Kingdom, and in them to have deſtroy'd in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect the whole Nation, more eſpecially the Church, and the Proteſtant Intereſt eſtabliſht therein. By all theſe Inſtances it doth abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appear as to the truth of the thing, <hi>That it is, and hath been all along, and by conſequence will be, more or leſs to the end of the World, the wont and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom of the Devil and his Inſtruments, to contrive and deſign the ruine and miſery of the Church and People of God, tho' by the wickedeſt and moſt bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous means that can be thought of, or invented:</hi> And we ſhall be further confirm'd in this, by conſidering the Reaſons upon which this is founded, which are ſuch as follow.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The moſt univerſal ground and reaſon, is that everlaſting Enmity, which is ſet and fixt, and that by God himſelf; between the two Seeds, the Seed of the Womon, and the Seed of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, that is, betwixt Chriſt and his Church on the one hand, and the Devil and his Angels, and all wicked Men, that are his Seed, on the other. This Enmity was fixt by God very early, even as ſoon as the Covenant was renewed with Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind thro' Chriſt after the Apoſtacy of <hi>Adam,</hi> as you will find, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. where God ſaith to the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:65060:8"/>Serpent, <hi>And I will put Enmity between thee and the Woman, and between thy Seed, and her Seed; it ſhall bruiſe thy head, and thou ſhalt bruiſe his heel.</hi> This was the main ground of the quarrel be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel Cain</hi> kill'd his Brother <hi>Abel;</hi> his nearneſs in Blood could not ſave him from an hand of violence; and the fundamental reaſon was, becauſe <hi>Cain</hi>'s works were evil, and his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's were righteous: And this hath ſuitably been the fundamental ground of all the Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions, and Maſſacres, and Burnings, and Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, that ungodly Men, in all Ages, have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercis'd towards the Members of the Church, whatever elſe hath been pretended, as the reaſon of them. But yet;</p>
            <p n="2">2. There are ſome other reaſons that may be given of this matter; as (1.) Becauſe that gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious perſons are by their words and example, a continual reproof of the evil practices of wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Men; they do by their words and example, reprove their Superſtitions and Idolatries, in matters of Religion, and their Hypocriſie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; as alſo their Wickedneſs and Profaneneſs in life and practice; and this wicked Men cannot bear; they look upon ſuch kind of reproof to be no better than a reproach; and therefore are apt to revenge it by any kind of violent practice whatſoever. Thus God's Atteſtation, which he
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:65060:9"/>gave to <hi>Abel</hi>'s faith and ſincerity in his Worſhip which he offer'd to God, was that, which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked <hi>Cain</hi> to that violent dealing, which he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards expreſſed towards his Brother. Thus the Chriſtians in the Primitive times, diſowning and reproving the Idols, that did then ſo much abound in the Heathen World, did provoke the Heathens ſo much to perſecute them to the death. And thus the Proteſtants reproving and diſowning the Superſtitious and Idolatrous pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices of the Papiſts, is that which hath eſpecially ſtirr'd up the Papiſts to all their Cruelties againſt them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Another ground is an inconſiſtency, it may be, in temporal intereſts and concerns; wicked Men do make Self their God, and Self-intereſt their <hi>Diana,</hi> which they chiefly adore; when there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this is croſt by any one, tho' it be done no other way, but by the performance of neceſſary duty, they are hereupon apt to be provok'd to endeavour Revenge, tho' in the moſt cruel way and manner. Thus that which provok'd <hi>Balak</hi> to procure <hi>Balaam</hi> to curſe the People of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> was a fear leſt they ſhould diſturb him in his Kingdom and Government: And that which hath eſpecially provok'd the Popiſh Party againſt the Proteſtants, is becauſe that by their Doctrine they touch the Pope's Crown, and the Fryers
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:65060:9"/>Bellies; if theſe had been let alone, as ſome have obſerved, <hi>Luther</hi> had not met with ſuch oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in his Preaching. Thus <hi>England</hi>'s ſtanding of old in the way of the Ambition of <hi>Spain,</hi> and its ſtanding of late in the way of the Ambition of <hi>France,</hi> hath been the main ground of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>'s Troubles from <hi>Spain</hi> formerly, and now from <hi>France;</hi> ſo that if we conſider theſe parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, it will appear to be no matter of wonder, <hi>That 'tis, and hath been all along, and by conſequence will be to the end of the World, the cuſtom of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil and his Inſtruments, to contrive, and deſign the ruine and miſery of the People and Church of God, though by the wickedeſt means that can be thought of, or invented:</hi> But I have further added,</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That the Church and People of God are from time to time, and ſhall be to the end of the World, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered from, and ſhall prevail againſt the Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances and Machinations of the Devil, and his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments.</hi> 'Tis true indeed, and muſt be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, that particular perſons, who are real Members of the Church of Chriſt, may be, and often have been brought to untimely Ends, by the machinations and contrivances of wicked Men in this kind; this is ſuitable to all Hiſtory &amp; Experience; and the Apoſtle confirms it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.36. quoting it out of <hi>Pſal.</hi> 44.22. <hi>As it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, for thy ſake are we killed all the day long; we
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:65060:10"/>are accounted as Sheep for the ſlaughtor;</hi> by which words he proves, that tribulation, and diſtreſs, and perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and famine, and nakedneſs, and peril, and ſword, may be the portion of the People of God; as he ſaith in the verſe before; this is evident likewiſe from what is ſaid, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.36, 37. <hi>Others had tryal of cruel mockings and ſcourgings, yea moreover of bonds and impriſonments; they were ſtoned, they were ſawn aſunder, were tempted, were ſlain with the ſword; they wandred about in Sheep-skins, and Goat-skins, being deſtitute, afflicted, tormented,</hi> &amp;c. But even in this caſe there are two things very conſiderable; 1. That as to ſuch as are perſecuted thus to death, they are hereby but haſtened to the enjoyment of a bleſſed Immortality, even as <hi>Abel</hi> was; tho' they may loſe their Heads in the quarrel, yet they do not loſe their Crown, but enjoy it ſo much the ſooner; <hi>nay in all theſe things,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>we are more than Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors, thro' him that hath loved us, Rom.</hi> 8.37. 2. 'Tis farther obſervable, that the Kingdom of Chriſt is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally the more encreaſed, and inlarged, occaſional<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from ſuch perſecutions; <hi>Sanguis Martyrum eſt ſemen Eccleſiae;</hi> 'twas an old obſervation, that the Blood of Martyrs was the ſeed of the Church: This <hi>Tertullian</hi> tells the Heathens, in his Apology, the more we Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians are mow'd down by the ſickle of death, the more we are increaſed, and grow up the thicker hereby: But,</p>
            <p n="2">2. It muſt be allow'd further, that as for particular
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:65060:10"/>Churches, they may poſſibly be utterly deſtroy'd and ſcatter'd by the violence of Perſecution; for God hath not given his promiſe to any particular Church, whether Congregational, Provincial, or National, that it ſhall always continue in the ſtate of a true Church of God; but then 'tis to be conſidered, 1. That God doth long preſerve ſome National and Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Churches, notwithſtanding all deſigns and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinations to the contrary; of which our Church of <hi>England</hi> hath been hitherto a ſingular, and ſtanding Inſtance. 2. When at any time he ſuffers the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of any particular Church, 'tis becauſe of ſome great provocations from that Church preceding; as he threatens the Church of <hi>Epheſus</hi> to remove her Candleſtick, becauſe of her forſaking her firſt love, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.4, 5. which threatning hath been ſince ſo ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accompliſht, that, as a late Writer obſerves unto us, there is not one Chriſtian Family now to be found in <hi>Epheſus.</hi> 3. When at any time it ſo falls out, that particular Churches are diſperſt and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy'd by the violence of Perſecution, yet even this falls out oftentimes to the good and benefit of the Univerſal Church, and the greater ſpreading of it, thoſe that are diſperſt by Perſecution, ſpreading the Goſpel for which they are perſecuted ſo much the more, where ever they go; as happen'd upon occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the perſecution, that was rais'd againſt <hi>Stephen, Act.</hi> 8.4. 'tis ſaid, that they that were ſcatter'd abroad
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:65060:11"/>upon that occaſion, went every where preaching the Word. And 'tis the obſervation of ſome, that the <hi>Turks</hi> breaking into <hi>Europe,</hi> cauſed ſeveral of the <hi>Greek</hi> Church, who were endow'd with much more Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing than was ordinarily found in the <hi>Latin</hi> Church, to betake themſelves towards the Weſtern parts of <hi>Europe;</hi> and this, amongſt other things, made way for the Reformation that followed, and this may ſerve for the caſe of particular Churches. But then,</p>
            <p n="3">3. As for the caſe of the Univerſal Church, certain it is, that no Perſecution ſhall ever be able to deſtroy it, and root it out of the World; God hath founded his Church upon a Rock; <hi>Thou art Peter,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>and upon this Rock</hi> of thy confeſſion, that I am the Son of God, <hi>will I build my Church, &amp; the Gates of Hell,</hi> all the Power, that is, and the Policy of Hell, <hi>ſhall never be able to prevail againſt it.</hi> 'Tis the original promiſe of God, that as the Seed of the Serpent ſhall be ſuffered to bruiſe the heel of the Woman, and her Seed, that is, that part of it that is here upon Earth; ſo the Seed of the Woman ſhall bruiſe the Serpents head; ſo that in the iſſue, the Church of God in general is ſure to be delivered from, and to prevail againſt the contrivances and machinations of the Devil, and his Inſtruments, according as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Behold God ſhall tread Satan under your feet ſhortly.</hi> And this is confirm'd by all Hiſtory and Experience. Thus the Church of God was at length delivered
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:65060:11"/>out of <hi>Egyptian</hi> Bondage, and <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and his Hoſt, who had perſecuted the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> and drowned their Infants, were drowned in the Red Sea. Thus God turned <hi>Balak</hi>'s deſign of a Curſe upon <hi>Iſrael</hi> into a Bleſſing. Thus the <hi>Jews</hi> were delivered from <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi>'s deſign'd Maſſacre, &amp; <hi>Haman</hi> and his Sons were hanged upon the Gibbet that was prepared for <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decai.</hi> Thus Chriſtianity was at length delivered from the Perſecutions of Heathen Idolaters, and the Heathens Idolatry was ſoon baniſht out of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Empire. Thus the effect of the miſcarrying de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> in Eighty eight, was, that it brought ſuch a declenſion upon their Power, as from which they have not recovered even to this day. Thus ſome have obſerved, that the Maſſacres in <hi>France</hi> were followed with a quick and wonderfully reviving of the Proteſtant Intereſt in that Nation, &amp; with miſerable calamities upon the Popiſh party therein; and what was the effect of the Barbarity of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Papiſts in their Rebellion, but miſerable ruine upon themſelves, and their Families? Thus to conclude, we were at this day, delivered from the intended ruine and deſtruction by Gun-powder, and the Conſpirators brought a juſt Execution upon themſelves, and Ruine upon their own Families; and which is more yet, the effect was, that it hath cauſed Popery to be much more abhorr'd ever ſince by the generality of this Nation: By all which Inſtances,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:65060:12"/>tis abundan tly made good, <hi>That the Church of God hath been from time time, and therefore ſhall be, no doubt, to the end of the World, delivered from, and ſhall prevail againſt the contrivances and machinations of the Devil, and his Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi> Now if the ground and reaſon of this ſhould be inquired, we have a ſufficient account of it in the</p>
            <p>3d Note before obſerv'd, <hi>That the whole honour of this matter is to be aſcribed to God, and it muſt be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged to be the effect of his Power and Operation.</hi> This is clearly intimated in the words of my Text, <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this time it ſhall be ſaid of</hi> Jacob, <hi>and of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>What hath God wrought?</hi> The Deliverance of God's People from time to time, is the work of God, and the effect of his Power; and therefore to him alone is the honour and glory hereof to be aſcribed.</p>
            <p>'Tis true indeed, in ſubordination to God, there may be ſome other account given of this matter, why God ſhould do thus much for his Church, and that we have intimated likewiſe in my Text, the Church of God is here ſaid to be <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Iſrael;</hi> whereby is ſignified,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That they are God's Covenanted People, a People that have a Covenant-Relation to God, and a Covenant Intereſt in him, to whom he hath made many gracious Promiſes, and hath confirmed them by his Word and Oath, which are two immutable things, in which 'tis impoſſible for God to lye.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:65060:12"/>
            <p n="2">2. They are a praying wreſtling People; they are <hi>Jacobs,</hi> they are ſuch as give the Almighty no reſt, &amp; therefore ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably as for ſuch as thus cry day and night unto him; as 'tis ſaid by Chriſt in the Parable, He will, tho, he ſeems to defer Deliverance, yet avenge them ſpeedily: Whence</p>
            <p n="3">3. It follows, that they are wont to be <hi>Iſraels,</hi> ſuch as have power with God, and Man, and do prevail; they have an Intereſt in God, in his Power, and Mercy, in his Attributes, and Promiſes: No wonder then, if he do in due time, create Deliverances for them; and therefore ſuitably <hi>not unto us, not unto us, but to God alone, be the praiſe of all his Delivering Mercy.</hi> More eſpecially,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Of this great Mercy and Deliverance, which he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed as on this day to our Forefathers, and in them up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, a mercy which contained many ſingular mercies in the bowels of it, even the enjoyment of whatſoever is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirable, to make our Lives comfortable here in this World, or in order to the ſecuring of our Eternal Welfare in that other World. But farther,</p>
            <p n="2">2. We have reaſon to bleſs God, that he hath ſtill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued to us, the fruit and benefit of this days Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, in the enjoyment of the Goſpel, together with the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of our Lives, Liberties and Properties, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all the Deſigns of the Popiſh Party to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray. We know that 'twas not long ſince, that a <hi>Conclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt</hi> was ready to be pronounced upon our Religion, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty and Properties, and that not only by our Enemies, in a way of exulting, but alſo by our ſelves, in a way of diffidence and deſpondency. And we know farther, that there is a Party mixt every where amongſt us even in our very Bowels, who deſire, and as far as they can, &amp; dare, are plotting, and contriving in effect, that thus it may be ſtill; and this, altho' 'tis more than probable, that by ſeeking the Ruine of the Nation in general, and the preſent Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, they do but hew at the Bow, upon which they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves do ſtand, and which, falling, may in the iſſue prove
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:65060:13"/>their own Ruine. But bleſſed be God, who hath hitherto ſo far appeared for us, a ſinful undeſerving People, as to raiſe us up a Temporal Saviour, and deliver in the nick of time; and hath hitherto afforded unto him, the ſame Mercy, that <hi>Jacob</hi> takes notice of, as afforded to <hi>Joſeph;</hi> as you will find, <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.23, 24. <hi>The Archers have ſorely grieved him, and ſhot at him, and hated him; but his Bow hath hitherto abode in ſtrength, and the arms of his hands were made ſtrong, by the hands of the mighty God of</hi> Jacob. And we may hope, that 'tis not for nothing, that God hath hitherto delivered our King, from ſo many Deaths and Dangers, but that the deſign of God, in theſe gracious Providences, is to reſerve and uſe him ſtill, in his due time, as an Inſtrument, for our more full deliverance from all our Fears and Dangers; and ſuitably, as the Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances, that we have already received, do engage us to, ſuch Inſtances of real Holineſs and Conformity to God's Will, and to ſuch hearty, and thorow Reformation, as may expreſs our Thankfulneſs to God, for Mercies al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready received, and reſtrain us from taking occaſion from paſt Mercies, to ſin the more againſt God, as too many have done; as if they thought themſelves delivered on purpoſe, to do all theſe Abominations: So if God ſhall (as we hope he will) make uſe of our King, as a means yet more fully to deliver us out of the hands of our Enemies; we ſhould in the mean time reſolve ſeriouſly, in the ſtrength of God, that the iſſue and effect ſhall be, that hereupon we will ſerve him, in Holineſs and Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs before him all the days of our lives; according to the prayer of holy <hi>Zechary</hi> to this purpoſe, <hi>That he would grant unto us, that we being delivered out of the hands of our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, might ſerve him without fear, in holineſs and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Which God of his mercy grant,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
